Hey robot makers. In this video I want to show you
how to make a rack and pinion system using Fusion
360. This is ideal for if you want to convert
rotational energy into a linear motion. Okay,
let's get started. So I'm over here in Fusion
360. What I'm going to do is create a new sketch
and then I'm going to create this on the top
face. Press C for circle. And I'm going to make
this 18 and 12. That's the outer diameter
that I want my gear to be within. So let's
see what options we have for this. So, I'm just
going to make that construction line. Okay. So,
if we now go over to utilities and click
on the add-ins and then scripts and addins,
there's a really useful thing that's called
Spurgeear. Now, the bottom one, we click on that,
we can see this is a Python program. I think
there's another version which is the C++ one. I'm
just going to go for the Python one. I don't think
it makes any difference whatsoever with what we're
doing here, but I'm going to press the run button
there. And what we will then get is this little
dialogue box over here. We've got a whole bunch
of different options that we need to select. So,
what I want to be able to do is specify the
absolute outer diameter of my gear that it fits
within. I know that it's got 10 teeth. So, I can
come along over here and type 10 in the number of
teeth. But this module, I need to understand what
that needs to be. Now, I could look at the bottom
pitch diameter down here. The pitch diameter
isn't the outer diameter. That's the you can see
there the pitch diameter is this kind of middle
circle. And what we're really wanting to do is
have an external perimeter defined rather than
this pitch diameter. So let's have a look how we
might do that. So over here in Excel, I've just
created a little sheet that can help us do some
of the little formulas. These are really simple
formulas, but I just wanted to show you how we
could do this. So the pitch diameter is actually
the module times the number of teeth. But what
if we want to understand what module do we want?
Let's work backwards from that. So the module is
actually this outer diameter divided by the number
of teeth plus two. So if we know what the number
of teeth are, we know what our outer diameter
is, which is 18 1/2. That gives us a module
of 1.54. So if we go back over to Fusion 360,
and let's type in 1.54 as our module. Now it's
saying there that the center hole is too large. We
just need to change that center hole to be 3 mm,
for example. Let's make the gear thickness three.
And this root fillet also needs to be under.9.
So let's just change that to 0.9. So we can see
there the pitch diameter is 15.4. Let's go back
to our spreadsheet and have a quick look there.
15.4. 15.4 is this diameter. This pitch diameter.
Let's just rename that to pitch diameter so that
we can see that. So that's correct. And our outer
diameter is still 18.5. So this pitch diameter is
the outer diameter kind of minus 2 teeth if you
like. Okay. So let's go back to Fusion 360. Let's
uh click okay. All those options are good. And if
we now look, we have a tooth which fits perfectly
within that circle. Okay. So typically what you
would want to do next to do the rack piece is we
want to copy this profile. But at the moment the
tooth isn't oriented very well for us to do that.
So we need to rotate this body. So if we open up
this spur here, we go to the body. And now that
we've got that selected, we can press M for move.
If we go up here to the rotate, we can select the
axis we want to rotate it on. And then we're free
to rotate this round. But how do we know what
the exact angle is that we want to rotate this
round? Well, it's going to be a function of how
many tooth we've got. So let's go over here and
just add an extra little thing. So the rotation
rotation angle is going to be 360° divided by the
number of teeth that we have and then divide that
whole by two. So 18° is what we need to rotate it
by. Let's go back to our model. Let's type in 18°.
We can now see that we've got these two top and
bottom teeth perfectly aligned. The next thing we
want to do is we want to copy this entire cog and
bring that down by the pitch diameter. So let's
do that. Let's click on that. Press M again to
copy. This time we're going to do a translate. And
if we remember what the pitch diameter was, if we
go back to our sheet there. So the pitch diameter
is 15.4. So if we move this now in the let's try
the y ais minus5.4. So we want to actually make
a copy of this. And you can see there because
we've moved it down by the pitch diameter those
teeth are overlapping which is exactly what we
want. So I'm going to click okay. We can now hide
that original body. And all we want to do next is
create a new sketch and just copy this profile. So
let's do that. So we're going to go back to solid.
Click on create new sketch. I'm just going to do
it on the top of this surface here. Going to zoom
in a little bit. And then I press P to project.
And we can project individual lines. So if I hover
there and just select, you can just see it's in
black there. That line. We'll do the same with
the top. Same with the side. Same with that little
piece. And then that last little curve. Let's just
do those two on the other side as well. And I'll
click okay. And I hide that body. You can see that
we've got the actual outline of that profile.
I'm just going to do L for line. And just do a
line between those two points there. And if we
hover over that, you can now see that we've got
a profile that's enclosed. So this this shape
here is a really interesting curve and that's
actually an involute curve. So I'm just going to
click finish sketch. Do E for extrude. I'm going
to extrude this tooth out by say 3 mm. And let's
just go back to the bodies so that we can select
that. So let's just go back to our tooth there and
see that kind of in 3D. So that's one tooth. Now
typically we want to have many teeth in the rack.
We don't tend to have just one. So what we need
to do is we need to replicate that. But before we
do that, let's go back into that sketch and let's
define how long is this rack going to be. So I'm
going to do a rectangle. I'm going to start there.
I'm going to drag this out. I want this to be
about 3 mm high and then say 190 mm long. So
it's going to be quite long, skinny rack there.
There we go. That's what it's going to look like
in its entirety. So now that we've got that, that
can help us when we're actually calculating how
many teeth we need. So let's now go to finish that
sketch. So, we need to extrude that sketch. So,
I'm going to go to the sketch that we've just
created, which is the sketch number four there.
And I'm going to extrude this out by 3 mm like
so. I'm doing this as a separate operation so that
we can actually replicate that tooth along. So,
now that we need to do is go to create pattern,
rectangular pattern, and we want to find
the feature that we created before. So,
let's go to features, and let's find that tooth
that we created originally. And then the axis is
going to be along along this direction. If we now
start pulling this out, you'll see that we get get
some teeth. And we need to have a certain number
of teeth. But what should the spacing be between
the teeth? Let's just go to a different view and
see the distance between the teeth is quite an
important calculation. So let's go back to our
spreadsheet and see what this distance between
the teeth should be. So it's actually the pitch
diameter times pi divided by the number of teeth.
So I've got a little calculation there which
does exactly that. So it's looking at this pitch
diameter which we have just there 15.4 times by pi
and then divide the whole of that by the number of
teeth. The number that we've got there is 4.84. So
4.84 is the number that we need to type into that
dialogue box. So we go back over there. Uh we need
to go to the spacing and the spacing needs to be
4.84. 4.84. So that gives us the correct spacing
between the teeth. But how many teeth do we need?
Well, we can actually eyeball this quite easily.
So, we know it's going to be at least double
that. So, let's go for 20 teeth. Oh, it's probably
going to be more like 30 or 40 teeth. Let's try 40
teeth. You can see that's just one more than we
need. So, let's just go to 39. That looks about
right for that length. There we go. Now, currently
all these teeth are not connected to our hole. So,
what we can do is we can select everything. We
can click on the combine and then we can just
make sure that that's a join operation and click
okay. And we've now just got the one body just
there. that one that we hidden, that was the
original original spurgeear, right? So now to
check that these actually match, let's enable that
body of that original one. And then we're going
to rotate it back by 18° to see that it actually
fits. Okay. So let's click on that, press M, go
to our rotation, select that middle piece there,
and then we're going to rotate it by, it doesn't
matter which tooth we select on there, 18°, and we
want that to be body. Let's click okay. Let's zoom
in. And we can see there that looks like a perfect
kind of mesh between the teeth. So that's going to
work just right. So we can now print out these
pieces and that will work just the way we expect
it to. So hope that helps you. I've often found
that this dialogue box is a little bit confusing
particularly when you want to specify the outer
diameter rather than having to calculate what the
pitch diameter is from these these numbers
and also trying to figure all that module
is. So hope you enjoyed this short video and I
shall see you next time. Bye for now. [Music]